Previously on Gotham...
You left me the virus.
You've got two options.
You can take the virus.
And find the strength
and get out of there.
Or you can make that
coffin your permanent home.
Fish! Why are you here?
I was alive.
Goodbye, Fish!
Then I was dead.
Let's try subject 13, shall we?
And then I was alive.
Impossible.
Nothing is impossible.
Things are looking up.
My little Penguin and I...
Will be leaving.
This detonator will
trigger the bomb.
Thousands will be
infected with a virus.
Let Gotham fall so you may rise.
I won't have him turn
you into a murderer.
No, you will press it.
When you're ready,
come and find me.
Oh, my.
What is that? WOMAN:
What's happening out there?
My money, my
savings. My savings...
Excuse me, what?
My money, my savings. I want them.
My money, my savings. My whole life.
What's your account number?
My money, my savings...
My money, my savings.
Uh, this account was
closed due to unpaid fees.
No, no, my money, my savings,
my life, everything! I have to...
You have no money,
the account is closed.
Give me my money, now!
Oh, God. Um, security!
Hey! What are you...
My money! My savings! Now!
Get out!
- Hey, man! Hey!
- Stop this!
Come here! Come
back! Buy our cookies!
Move on!
Killer.
You're a killer.
Killer!
- Jim?
- Yeah.
You okay?
Fine.
I'm fine, Harvey.
Listen, I hate to do this to you, pal.
But I'm gonna have to ask for your gun.
This virus is tearing the city apart.
You need me. I can control this.
That's why I'm not
asking for your badge.
Some of the guys are talking.
These cops are gonna be watching
you for the smallest sign. Okay?
And if you've got a gun,
they'll be double jumpy.
It's for your own protection.
Any word on Lee?
Nada. What happened
after the bombing?
A mob of infected swarmed the clock
tower. She disappeared in the chaos.
I don't get it. She went
through all that effort
to get you infected with
the virus, then she just bolts?
She saw I was fighting it. She's
waiting for me to give over to it.
Prove her wrong.
Where's Bruce?
Detective Gordon.
Alfred. Has he said anything?
No, no, he just
sits there staring.
I need to talk to him, Harvey.
We're sure that's not the clone?
No, that's Bruce.
God knows what those bastards done
to him, but he's utterly brainwashed.
Are you really the best
person to talk to him?
I mean, from what you said,
you killed his mentor or something.
He might be a bit peeved.
Listen, whatever they did to
him, that is Bruce Wayne in there.
That boy is stronger than
you can possibly imagine.
I just need to make
him remember who he is.
As long as he doesn't
leave the precinct.
Harvey, something
you need to see.
An antidote? Lucius,
I could kiss your face.
Before you do that. I don't
actually have the formula.
But there is an antidote.
That's what you're saying?
I was going through the papers you
recovered from the Owl leader's house.
They suggest that while Strange was
working to weaponize the Tetch virus,
he was also working
on a parallel project,
tailoring different antiviral
agents to his own ends.
Strange was
designing an antidote.
That makes sense.
The Court was careful to protect its
own. They would've wanted a safeguard.
We need to talk to Strange. Is he
still here, or has he been moved?
Uh, well, when you
were buried in the coffin
and the city was about
to be virus-bombed,
some decisions had to be made.
Harvey!
I told Alfred to
question Strange.
In exchange for him telling us where
the bombing was gonna go down,
Alfred let Strange walk. Yes,
I'm blaming it on the butler!
All right. Strange is a weasel.
He'd try to get as far
away from this as possible.
Union Station is shut down.
Downtown train station's our best bet.
Yeah. Wait up!
Harvey?
Lucius, I know what you're gonna
say. All right? He can handle this.
Hell, Barnes had the virus
for weeks before anyone knew.
What I was gonna
say, from all I see here,
Strange's virus is an accelerated
version of the Tetch virus.
Why do you think people
are reacting so quickly?
Gordon isn't going to be
able to fight this for long.
Well. We'll just have
to wait and see, huh?
You keep working
on that antidote.
One second, one second!
One ticket at a time.
Sir, excuse me!
Oh!
Excuse me!
Oh, no.
I think you mean,
"Hello, Fish. I miss you."
And don't worry, sweetheart.
The fun has just begun.
As the flames of hedonism
licked the very
foundation of its society,
Nero played and sang
at the destruction of Troy.
I will say this about
the Court of Owls,
they have style.
Not to mention, they've handed
us the perfect opportunity.
For what?
The city is in total disarray.
What better time to
consolidate power?
Barbara?
I have told you, again and again, I
have no interest in running Gotham,
- I only want...
- To kill Penguin. Yes.
I got it the first
billion times.
And where is he now? Oh,
that's right, with Fish Mooney.
- So we find her.
- And then what?
You blast through her army of
goons until you get to Oswald?
You're gonna need muscle, honey.
- Which you provide.
- Oh.
So you expect my help.
But when I need yours
to take advantage of an
opportunity of a lifetime,
nothing.
Baby,
listen, all I ask
is that you use
this beautiful
big brain of yours
to help me finally
get this city under my thumb,
and afterwards, I will help you
pry Penguin away from Fish.
Deal?
I will give you a day.
I thought we were friends.
When the Court of Owls
calls, one does not refuse.
Still, I'm not upset.
I knew when your old masters summoned
you it was to cook up some horror.
And here's the
thing. I need horror.
They're responsible
for all of this, aren't they?
At the behest of The Court,
I weaponized a virus that
releases a person's darkest urges.
Thousands have been infected.
So where is this virus?
I know there's more.
It has all been used.
Please, I must go!
Don't. You will
give me the virus.
You will make me the
army you promised.
You will do everything I say
until this city is in
the palm of my hand.
Are we clear?
Yes, madam.
Sorry, folks, this
exit's off... Ah!
I'll look around for the station
cops, see if they found Strange.
Hello?
Oh, jeez.
He's right here.
This is Gordon.
Hi, Jim. I was just checking in.
Seeing how you're feeling.
Crazy day, huh?
- Lee, where are you?
- Somewhere very familiar to you.
I know how you're feeling.
All that blood rushing through your veins,
your heart beating faster and faster.
Listen to me.
You need to turn
yourself in. It's not safe.
The infected are being
killed all over the city.
Wow, you're really
fighting this, huh?
You know, you don't have to.
The cage is finally
open, Jim. You're free.
- No.
- I thought you loved me.
I thought you wanted
us to be together.
Not like this.
Well, this is the only way, Jim.
Just listen to the whispers.
Killer. Killer.
They'll lead you to me.
Tell you who you are.
Killer.
That's not who I am.
I wonder what they're saying.
That you like hurting
people? Killing people?
Killer.
See how well I know you, Jim?
Now I'm gonna go have some fun.
We'll catch up soon.
Promise.
Killer. Killer.
You're a killer.
Jim? Jim.
Someone spotted Strange.
Just don't shoot any innocent
bystanders. Or me. Especially me.
GCPD!
Don't move! Fish?
What a surprise.
My goodness,
Harvey. You look awful.
It's good to see you, too.
We just want Strange.
You can walk away.
Yeah. No.
Fish, I know in
your own sick way,
you love this city, and
Gotham is bleeding to death.
We need this dirtbag to fix it.
Enough talking. Hand him over.
He has it.
It's in his eyes.
He has the virus.
Really?
So, tell me, James,
what's it feel like?
Like it's taking all my
will power not to kill you.
My! Harvey, when you say
Hugo here can save the city,
does that mean there's
a cure for this virus?
Fish, I swear to God
if you don't step back,
I will shoot you and these two
nimrods right here, right now!
Hugo, is it true?
That you're the only one
that can stop this madness?
Mmm-hmm.
Obviously, I can't
give him up now.
Fine. You've had your chance.
Did you really think that I
would come without backup?
You're a killer.
Jim, dial it down, buddy.
Victor, looks like our little
Detective Gordon is overheating.
Perhaps, you should
cool him off. Both of them.
Marvelous.
Just marvelous.
There he is, the
real James Gordon.
Nice to meet you at last.
There we go, Master Bruce.
Two lumps just how you like it.
You hungry, mate?
Can I whip you up a sandwich?
Anyway, if all goes well,
we should be able to head
back to Wayne Manor tomorrow.
Although I was thinking
that we could go abroad.
We could go to Switzerland.
I mean, we used to go with your
mum and dad this time of year...
Stop it.
Your attempts to elicit
an emotional response
by reminding me of shared
memories is clumsy and pathetic.
Oh.
The last memory I have is
of you killing the best friend
and teacher I ever had.
You mean that old
geezer that kidnapped you,
poisoned your mind, and tried
to turn you into a mass murderer?
Let me tell you something,
Master Bruce, that man lied to you.
Him and his bloody
Court of Owls,
they tried to use you, they
tried to manipulate you.
You say he was a liar.
How?
By taking away the pain
I've carried for years?
By giving me revenge against the
people who killed my mother and father?
That's more than you ever did.
Anyway, the Court of
Owls does not matter.
They merely paved the way
for the one who is to come.
What do you mean?
Who... Who's coming?
You'll see.
- I should cook him.
- They want him alive.
So I'll just cook part of him.
No, my dear, let's be calm.
You don't have
that kind of control.
And you do? In my hands,
this flamethrower is a scalpel.
Fine. We'll each take a foot.
- Whoever goes above the ankle loses.
- You're on.
Let me... No, no, no! Stop!
Miss Mooney! Miss Mooney!
Mooney's busy!
I'm here now.
Also, I think your children
are angry with you.
- Mr. Cobblepot.
- It's understandable.
You made them what they are,
then abandoned them.
You are working
with Miss Mooney?
We're partners.
But you tried to kill her.
And she forgave me.
I know, surprised me, too.
But Mooney, is not the old
Mooney. She has evolved.
And she has a vision for Gotham.
She sees a city where
people like myself,
Victor, Bridgit,
freaks, are in charge.
And you are gonna
help us achieve that.
- I can't.
- Wrong, Professor!
This virus is tearing
Gotham apart!
That makes your antidote the
most valuable thing in the city!
We could demand half of Gotham
and the city council would
deliver it to us on a platter.
So, I'm going to ask you once,
where is it?
If I tell you where
the antidote is,
I have nothing.
I can't.
You can torture me all you want.
Okay.
What?
You know, when I was in
Arkham, I was tortured daily.
No. Well, that was
therapy, Oswald.
Therapy.
And that device you used
to administer the therapy,
remember that?
It gave the sensation that
your head was being torn open
so that hot lava could be
poured directly into your brain.
Afterwards, just thinking of it
would make me physically ill.
So, naturally, I had to have it!
One moment, Oswald.
- No!
- All right, all right!
I'll tell you anything you need to
know. I'll tell you where the antidote is.
I know.
But not just yet, okay?
Or what?
They're not answering at the
precinct. They must be overwhelmed.
Well, we're not
shooting our way out.
Killer.
Jim. Take it easy.
Someone will come!
Yeah! And by then Mooney will have
gotten Strange to give her the antidote.
We're running out of time!
Killer.
Killer. Killer.
I knew you could do it.
Jim!
Fight the damn virus!
Not my car. That's my car.
Let me drive.
Alvarez, spread the word, Mayor
James has called in the National Guard.
We don't want any soldiers
getting shot by mistake.
Leave me alone.
The hell's wrong with you?
Alvarez. Talking to you.
I said, leave me alone!
So, I will ask you
again. Who's coming?
I mean, I thought the man that I
dispatched at Wayne Enterprises
was the leader of
the Court of Owls?
I want you to leave.
Yeah, well, that ain't
gonna happen, is it, mate?
You can't rid of me that easy.
You have to
remember who you are.
I know who I am.
I have a destiny!
Now, you listen to me.
That man that wanted
you to detonate that bomb,
whatever he promised you,
freedom from pain, power, none of it,
none of it was real. I want
you to remember what is real.
I know what's real!
I got vengeance for my
parents' murder. That's real!
No.
No, that's not real.
What's real is every time that
you were sick when you were a kid,
your mum used to sit up with you all
night and read to you till you fell asleep.
That's real.
Or when you were seven and
you took your silly rowing boat out
and you got lost in that storm
and me and your dad were out
shouting and screaming, losing our minds,
and when your dad
found you, how he cried.
That's real.
Yes, your parents died in
that alley three years ago,
and maybe that man took
away the pain of that night,
but there is no life, there
is no love, without pain.
He could not touch the love
that your mum and dad gave
you, that you still have in you.
You still have in here.
Same love that I have for you.
I love you, Master Bruce.
I would do anything for
you. I would die for you.
You must find that love again.
Come back to me, Master Bruce.
- Thank you very much.
- No problem.
Excuse me.
Oh, bloody hell.
What I'm saying is, if Penguin
and Fish have hooked up,
things are gonna
get real bad, real fast.
You wanna run?
No. I'm saying maybe she takes
care of Barbara and Nygma for us.
I mean, we could
even help things along.
Send word to Fish about
where Babs is weak.
This is our shot.
I'm not ready.
What the hell is she doing here?
Well, this is a strange day.
Never thought I'd
see you in here.
I had some time to kill
while my ex sees the light.
Figured I'd have a little fun.
Where's Babs?
- What do you want with her?
- None of your business, errand boy.
I'm sorry, what did you call me?
I'm sorry, you're
not an errand boy.
You're more of a shoeshine boy.
They should give you
a little stand in the front.
Cute little hat. That's
more your speed.
Right. Out.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
You've got the virus.
Wow, you're not as
dumb as I've heard.
Are there any other glaringly
obvious remarks you'd like to make?
How about I cut your lungs
out and show them to you?
Wow. That's incredibly
vivid. I'd like to see you try it.
But I'm here for your
boss, the crazy blond.
She's not my boss.
Uh-huh. I may have a virus making
me freakishly strong and mildly insane,
but even I know that you
were a sidekick to your brother,
and you're a
sidekick to Barbara.
So, can you send
her a message for me,
would you?
Your boss.
Tell her next time I see her, I'm
gonna rip her head right off her body.
Bye, now.
What, you need help?
Go back inside.
Gotham's curfew...
Got him.
Sundown.
All individuals must
remain indoors.
Any activity outdoors will be
considered criminal activity.
Clear here! Let's go,
let's go! Let's move out.
He's following
directions or something.
Gotta find out who's controlling
him. Who's brainwashed him.
And then what?
I'm gonna kill the bastard.
You two wait here.
Professor, if this is a trap,
you will soon find yourself
hanging with the rest of the meat.
It's no trap.
I tested earlier versions of the
virus and the antidote on livestock.
I made sure to set
aside a successful batch.
This place gives me the creeps.
I like it.
It's concentrated.
Once you dilute it,
there is enough here to cure
every infected person in Gotham.
Hmm.
Oswald,
you and I will rule
this city together.
Yes. But first, I have to kill
Ed Nygma. He has to die.
Oh, he will.
And all those who
try to stand in our way.
What's this?
Who's there?
Show yourself.
Who are they?
Don't look at me, I don't know.
Really? That's all you've got?
Hand over the antidote. Now.
I want the Strike Force and all
available units there now! I'm on my way.
Reports of an ice storm and fireball
in the East Side Slaughterhouse.
- You think maybe...
- Just drive the damn car!
Sweet mother of mercy.
Killer, killer.
You damn fool!
Fish!
Oswald...
It's okay, it's okay, it's...
We can get you some help.
No. No. No.
I've done this enough
times to know I'm finished.
No. Do not say that!
We will get you help.
Listen to me!
Listen to me.
Make this city yours.
Or you burn it to the ground.
People call me a monster.
You! Jim Gordon, you're the...
You're right. I am a monster.
GCPD!
Arrest 'em. All of 'em!
Strange, you better tell me that
you can make more of that antidote.
Yes, yes.
I just need one thing.
How's it hanging?
You sure about this?
According to my sources,
Fish Mooney and the GCPD are scrambling
to recover the antidote to this virus.
But Fish is dead.
And Hugo Strange, who
designed the antidote,
is setting up a lab in the GCPD.
But they are missing one
very, very important element.
So, yes, I am sure that this bozo
is the key to controlling Gotham.
Are you my saviors?
Are you the ones to set me free?
Not exactly.
Let's make Gotham beg.
Seek out the Yuyan building.
Find the demon's head.
Fulfill your destiny.
Right. Find Bullock. Let
him know where we are.
I'm gonna follow Bruce.
I wouldn't touch that, Bruce.
You know who I am?
Who do you think told the
Sensei to send you here?
He's dead.
He was murdered.
He died.
But he completed his task.
The Court of Owls is
destroyed, Gotham burns,
and you are here.
He told me to complete my
training. To find the demon's head.
You already have, Bruce.
I'm the one you seek.
I'm the demon's head.
I am Ra's al Ghul.
Why have you come to me, Bruce?
The Sensei told me to seek you out.
That you would complete my training.
And did the Sensei tell
you who I am, what I seek?
I know you're not a
part of the Court of Owls.
That you only use them.
But I don't know why.
Then know that I have been alive
more years than you can imagine.
That I have seen and done things
that would shake the core
of everything you believe.
That I'm thought to be a demon.
A saint.
A ghost.
But for all my
years, all my travels,
there is one thing
that I have never found.
A true heir.
But I need to know
if you're ready.
I am.
The Sensei trained me.
Are you?
He set you a task.
He asked you to be the one that released
the virus that now envelops this city.
You failed.
I would have, but...
But Alfred, he...
He distracted me!
I know.
And that's why I'm gonna give you
another chance to complete your journey.
Oh, don't look so
surprised, Master Bruce.
I told you, you couldn't
get rid of me that easy.
I just got a bit sloppy.
Got a bit of ring rust.
Let these little ninja
monkeys get one over on me.
You all right, mate?
What are you come as?
Enough.
This man is your past, Bruce.
Now, embrace your future.
Kill him.
Join me.
Fulfill your destiny.
He's wrong, Master Bruce.
There's no other way to put it.
He's wrong.
Your destiny is to
be Bruce Wayne.
And one day you're
gonna remember that.
And you're gonna remember
how much I love you.
I remember the first time your
mum and dad brought you home.
They were so exhausted.
And they gave you to me.
This tiny defenseless
little creature.
And they said, "Look after
him." And I said, "Sure,"
and I scooped you up in my arms,
and I held you, and
you opened your eyes,
and you looked at me.
And at that moment, I decided
that I would do anything
for you. Anything.
So if this is what you need to
do, Master Bruce, you crack on.
You do it.
Join me.
Alfred! Alfred! Alfred!
Alfred! No!
Alfred!
You've broken through
your conditioning.
Impressive.
You don't control me anymore.
I will never be your heir.
On the contrary,
your strength only confirms
what the prophecy has foretold.
An heir to serve as my
knight in the darkness.
I will never follow you!
You made me kill Alfred.
Use the waters, Bruce.
Our time will come.
Bruce.
Alfred. Alfred. Alfred. Alfred.
A city-wide lockdown
continues to remain in effect,
with Gotham officials urging
people to stay inside their homes.
As thousands of infected
citizens continue their rampage...
Lee. Where are you?
Why? You miss me?
City's not safe.
Mmm. Well, that's
why I'm packing a bag.
What are you talking about?
I'm leaving Gotham. And I
want you to come with me.
I'll take your silence as a yes.
Lee. You can't leave. There
are checkpoints all over the city.
Who you trying to convince, Jim?
I can hear it in your voice.
You want this as much as I do.
We can finally be
together. Without judgment,
or secrets or jealousy.
After everything
we've been through,
don't we deserve that?
I am leaving on
the afternoon train,
and I want you with me.
But I want the real you.
So tell me you'll
stop fighting it.
Tell me I won't lose you again.
Tell me you'll be there.
I'll be there.
Hey, Jim.
Where are we with Tetch?
Barbara and Nygma gave the
Mayor's office a list of demands.
Friend snuck me a copy.
They also threatened to kill Tetch
if we tried to take him back by force.
Half of these would
bankrupt the city.
The alternative being
there's no city left to bankrupt.
We don't have any cards to
play, partner. We got no moves.
Yes, we do.
- Him.
- Penguin?
This entire list is
Barbara's except for him.
Penguin is the only
thing Nygma cares about.
- The question is, how much?
- No way.
- There is no way we're turning him over.
- Why not?
Because we don't
have the authority
to broker some kind of secret
deal behind the city's back.
Much less one that leads to the
imminent death of its former mayor.
Nygma would betray Barbara and
hand over Tetch if given half the chance.
I need to save Lee.
I don't have much time,
Harvey. It's now or never.
You know, one of these
days, I'm gonna say, "Never."
- Hello.
- Nygma.
It's Gordon. I'm calling with
a proposition. Can you talk?
I can listen.
We need to kill her.
How much longer
are we gonna wait?
Come on. Nygma
chopped off your hand.
He almost killed me.
And now, Barbara's
partners with him?
That's the mother
of all insults.
The city is gonna pay us a
lot of money to get Tetch back.
We need to let that play out
before we do anything rash.
I know you two were close.
But whatever you had,
she treats you like dirt now.
She treats us both
like dirt and you know it.
She doesn't
deserve your loyalty.
What are you two
whispering about?
- Nothing.
- Mmm.
Any word from City Hall?
Trust me. We're
about to own this town.
Parts of it, quite literally.
Where is Ed?
He was just here a minute ago.
Tetch?
Nygma!
- How could you let this happen?
- Us?
You're the one that trusted him.
I asked you to do one thing.
Watch a man tied to a chair!
You idiots can't even do that.
Where are we going? - Shut up!
Look, I'm not trying
to aggravate you.
It's just, this doesn't exactly have
an above-the-board feeling about it.
- What's going on?
- Barbara and Nygma have Tetch.
- They're ransoming the city.
- So what does that have to do with me?
You're handing me over to him. You
can't. You can't. You cannot do this!
It's a small price to
pay for saving the city.
Yeah. For you. For me,
it's a very large price!
Look, he cannot be trusted.
You're risking everything
based on the word of a sociopath!
Yeah, yeah. Get in the car.
What? It's gonna be fine.
Yeah. Penguin, Nygma,
Tetch, all in the same place
for a high-stakes hostage swap?
What could possibly go wrong?
Do you mind?
Look, if I'm gonna be
the city's sacrificial lamb,
the least you can do is lead me
to the slaughter with a little dignity.
No.
You don't think that I can cause
you trouble once we're inside?
You do and I'll kill you.
No. You won't. Not
before you have Tetch.
Not before the
exchange goes smoothly.
And after that, what do
you care what happens?
Let's just get this over with.
- Thank you.
- Shut up.
My three favorite men.
Don't feel bad, Oswald.
Your death at my
hands was inevitable.
Is that what you told
yourself last time?
I'm assuming the grenade's
not a fashion statement.
Precaution.
You three try
anything, I pull the pin...
Kaboom! No more Tetch.
No hope for an antidote.
Little crude, don't you think?
Enough! Let's get this done.
You're infected! How wonderful.
Nygma!
Did you really think you
could get away with this?
I knew you'd figure out
that this was about Oswald,
but how'd you figure
out where we are?
Please. You know how
many cops I got on the payroll?
Oh, baby, you might
wanna use your inside growl
whilst making secret
calls inside the GCPD.
Now, hand him over.
Go!
Let him go! Let him go!
We need to get Tetch!
Now.
That little bastard.
Coming through. Move
out of the way. Rita, move.
All right, let's have a look.
Whoa. What did you
do to cauterize this?
I don't know. Is he
going to be okay?
We'll do everything we can. What's
your relationship to the patient?
Doctor, BP's falling.
We're family.
All right. Let's get him typed,
cross-set and prepped for OR.
It looks pretty good.
I'll call the station!
Grab Tetch!
Split up.
Jim.
You and the ex
are infected, huh?
I heard Lee wants to remove
my pretty little head from my body.
Is it weird that kinda
makes me like her?
You thinking about ripping
anyone's head off, Jim?
I bet you are.
You're so close.
The next time you give
in, the virus will have you.
Stop talking!
Jim!
Come out, come out,
wherever you are...
Hey. There's no back door. No
loading dock. No way this ends well.
The virus will give you
all the strength you need.
It's the only option.
Give in to the darkness.
I said...
Killer.
Stop talking.
You want to kill
me, that I can see,
but without my blood
no antidote will there be!
Fight it, Jim.
I don't know if I can.
He's right. We need him.
Yeah. But not all of him.
Where are they? What happened?
What'd he do?
Oh, Jim. You sick bastard.
Where's the lab tech?
Where's the lab tech? Come
on, come on. Here, here.
What? You've never seen a
Mason jar filled with blood before?
Go! Back to work!
You okay?
Oh! Oh!
He's awake. I
was getting lonely.
Where are we?
We ran into a police blockade.
Had to hunker down a minute.
Where are you taking me?
I don't know. I'm sort
of improvising here.
Why? You have
someplace you have to be?
Does it matter?
I imagine you're planning
on dragging this out.
There are so few moments
of pure joy in one's life.
I feel compelled
to savor this one.
You mean gloat.
Yes. I do.
It was always one of your
least attractive qualities, Oswald.
- It's killing you, isn't it?
- What?
To know that you are not
as smart as you think you are.
All of that planning to drive me
crazy, strip me of everything I had.
Revealing yourself with a 'ta-da!'
and shooting me by the river.
That plan was perfect,
and you know it.
You failed.
I am still alive and you are
handcuffed in the backseat.
And now you will never be
able to correct your mistake.
I guess not.
Now that they have Tetch's
blood, they can make the antidote,
and after what we tried to pull, the
whole city's gonna be gunning for us.
Hell, I'm surprised the cops haven't
busted down our door already.
Relax. They've got
better things to do.
What are we supposed to do now?
We split up, go to the
safe house and regroup.
Regroup? For what?
For whatever the
hell I tell you to do.
I'm not waiting anymore.
She's broken every promise
she's ever made to you. To us.
I know.
The safe house is the
perfect place to do it.
Okay.
I'll take care of everything.
No.
We do it together.
Yeah.
Ooh.
Kowalski and Burrows
are gonna be pissed.
Tetch's blood is good.
The lab guys are starting work
on an antidote as we speak.
I need to get to Lee. How
long? How long before it's ready?
They said we could
head there now.
Where is it?
Detective Gordon, just in time.
If you'll take a seat
and roll up your sleeve.
We have a dose ready for you right
now. The others will be ready shortly.
I need two.
Sorry. We could only make one
of these single-shots so quickly.
No. Two.
All of Tetch's blood is in
the centrifuge machines.
- The process can't be interrupted.
- You're a killer.
Just one or two hours, max. You
can still catch Lee before she leaves.
- There's not enough time.
- Ow!
- Jim?
- Killer.
Jim?
Don't make me. Jim! No, Jim! Jim!
Damn it! Someone call the bullpen.
Bruce.
I heard about Alfred.
Is he gonna be okay?
Go home, Selina.
What happened?
No.
- No. You don't get to do this.
- Do what?
Walk back into my life. You
think I need your pity? I don't.
- That's not why I'm here.
- You wanna know what happened?
- You wouldn't understand.
- Why?
Because I'm not desperate
to believe in something?
Because you don't believe in
anyone or anything but yourself.
It's called surviving.
And unlike you,
I know who I am.
I don't need anyone to tell me.
What are you even
doing here, Selina?
You don't give a damn about Alfred,
and you sure as hell don't care about me.
I know you better than that.
Yeah.
I thought you did.
Have a nice life!
Lee.
I don't like to be kept waiting.
You're still fighting it.
I can help you with that.
We both know
that's not what I want.
I want you.
I want you and
all your darkness.
Give in.
Give in to your
darkness. Be free.
Don't you get tired of making
the same mistake over and over?
You think I'm making a mistake?
Well, instead of killing me
when you had the chance,
you've decided to feed your ego.
You wanna talk ego? "Riddler"?
You will always fail, Oswald,
because you will always let
your base emotions drive you.
Hate...
Anger...
Fear...
- Love.
- Shut up.
You wanna know why I could
never love someone like you, Oswald?
- I'm warning you.
- Because you are a
spoiled child who throws a tantrum
any time he doesn't get what he wants.
Especially when what he
wants doesn't want him back.
You're right. I shouldn't
have waited. But unlike you,
I am in the position
to rectify my mistake.
Prepare for one massive tantrum.
No! That is not possible!
It is my turn! It is
my turn to kill you!
Like I said.
You will always fail.
Because you'll never change.
Maybe. But at least
I know who I am.
That day, by the
edge of the river,
that was the moment
you were reborn,
and that was a lie.
Your entire persona
is based on a lie!
And there is nothing
you can do to change that.
Actually, maybe there is.
Attention! All travelers must
pass through security checkpoints
before boarding the trains.
Please report anyone who might
be displaying signs of infection
at the nearest checkpoint
or security officer...
Hey, this isn't a
public entrance.
Oh, crap!
Police! Excuse me! Police! Move aside!
Police! Move, move! Get out of my way!
He's trying to stop us.
You can't let him.
I'll see you on the train.
Police, police! Move!
Out of the way, move! Jim! Jim!
Now we're gonna be
delayed, aren't we?
You gonna shoot me, Harvey?
This isn't you!
It is.
Please, don't make me do this!
Lee and I belong together.
I know. I know how
bad you want that.
To forget about everything that
happened, but you can't, it's not real!
This is who I am!
- This is who I've always been!
- No, it's not!
Who you are is a choice.
It always has been, it still is!
This is who you are.
You're the best cop
I ever worked with.
The best friend I've ever had.
If you love Lee...
Go save her.
Tickets?
To our great adventure.
I love you, Lee.
No!
What have you done?
Really? A hacksaw?
Even your disposal
tactics are idiotic.
Guess I'm just old fashioned.
Did you really think I
wouldn't figure it out?
The two of you have been
whispering like teenagers for weeks.
Oh, Butchie. You
shouldn't have waited.
Oh, believe me, if it weren't for Tabby,
you'd have been dead a long time ago.
You're trying to tell me she
had nothing to do with this?
- That's right.
- Oh, so you've just
gone behind her back, have you?
I was gonna hit you before
we got to the safe house.
Play dumb when you didn't show.
Leaning into your strengths.
You want to know why you're
always taking shots at me?
The giant size of the target?
It's because for
all your tough talk,
you miss her.
You miss her
loyalty. Her strength.
She made you
better and you know it.
You sacrificed that, for what?
To play queen for a day?
Pathetic.
If it helps? You never
deserved her in the first...
I guess we'll see.
I don't know if you can hear me.
But if you can,
Alfred, you need to fight.
I don't know what I
would do without you.
Alfred, please.
Please don't leave me.
Here we are. Again.
Wow.
I have to tell you,
this feels really great.
Glad I could help.
Any last words?
I'm fine for now.
I beg your pardon?
I'll wait.
I'm going to kill you, Oswald.
There is no later. If you
have something to say,
now is the time!
Duly noted.
Whatever. I'm not
letting you ruin this for me.
You don't have anything to say,
but I do.
Goodbye, Oswald.
I removed the bullets
when you were knocked out.
Right before I called them.
In the backseat,
the pin I used to
unlock my cuffs?
My tie pin. I thought
it should be personal.
You were just trying to make
me think I had the upper hand.
It all fell into place.
How did you know that Barbara
would show up at the warehouse?
I didn't.
If it wasn't for her...
Gordon would have turned me
over, and I'd most likely be dead.
But fortune favors the bold.
You said you called them
after you knocked me out.
You knew that
I'd bring you here.
I know you, Ed.
I may be driven by my emotions,
but you are driven by
something much more predictable.
A desperate, compulsive need to complete
what you've started in exacting fashion.
Why don't you just
kill me, Oswald?
You were the one time
I let love weaken me,
and I want you around
as a constant reminder
to never make
that mistake again.
No!
Barbara?
Butch?
Was killing Nygma really
that important to you?
Did you kill Butch?
He said you didn't have anything
to do with him trying to kill me.
Is that true?
What does it matter?
All right, for argument's sake,
let's say I haven't
been the best friend.
Do you think we could put this
behind us and move forward?
Did you kill Butch?
That doesn't sound like a yes.
I need to know.
It's the only way we'll
be able to move forward.
Yes.
I killed him.
But it's not like you
gave me a choice!
There's always a choice!
How many times have I told you
not to bring a whip to a gunfight?
Now, we can move forward.
The Tetch antidote has
been released over the city
with a 90% cure rate
with individual antidotes
now being manufactured
and given to GCPD officers...
- You're awake!
- Ow! Ow!
I'm sorry, Alfred.
Wasn't your fault, was it?
I completely lost my way.
I've been trying to find
who I am for so long,
searching for some
greater meaning.
I don't know who I am, Alfred.
Who am I supposed to be?
I can't help you
with that one, mate.
You're a man now.
You gotta find your own path.
I'm not like you.
You've always been
so sure of who you are.
Oh, I don't know about that.
I've been through
some very dark places.
As have you.
You need to find your true north
and let that guide you.
What's yours?
You.
It's always been you.
You gotta find something
that you really care about,
and you protect it at all costs.
And when you find it...
You'll never be lost again.
And though the arrival of the
antidote is certainly welcome news,
the death and the destruction
the virus left in its wake
will no doubt reverberate
through the city for years to come.
Yeah?
Is Barbara around?
No.
And she's not coming back.
What do you want?
I'm not sure.
I just know I'm tired
of just surviving.
I want more.
I wanna move up.
Figured this was a
good place to start.
I'm at a bit of a
crossroads myself.
You hungry?
You buying?
Give it a whirl.
That is the logo
for my new club.
What are we going to call it?
The Iceberg Lounge.
Clever. 'Cause you're
nicknamed Penguin, right?
There's that.
And then,
there's the club's
centerpiece attraction.
Lee?
Jim, I knew if I saw you I might
not have the courage to leave.
And I need to.
I finally understand Gotham in a
way I suspect you always have.
It's a place where the
strongest and most cunning rule.
Where the cost of survival
is paid for by others.
And everyone feels alone.
Having the virus showed
me the city as it truly was.
As I truly was.
In so many ways,
the virus made me feel reborn.
He's a gangster. Probably
got what he deserved.
- He is?
- Sure. That's Butch Gilzean.
Really? His chart lists his
birth name as Cyrus Gold.
Cyrus Gold?
Must have changed
it at some point.
But if having the virus
allowed Gotham to
embrace its worst self...
The cure should remind
us there is always hope,
a chance to remember who we
can be, rather than who we are.
I don't know if Gotham deserves
saving, but I do know one thing.
If anyone can save it,
it's you.
And in return, I believe
it can save you as well.
And then maybe one day,
it will send you back to me.
Until then,
love always,
Lee.
Can I come in, Captain?
No.
You threw me
against a train car.
I know.
Two, actually. I felt
like a freakin' cartoon!
I am really sorry about that.
You see Lee?
She's gone. She left Gotham.
You okay?
I will be.
You want to get a drink?
- It's noon.
- I didn't ask you what time it was,
I asked if you
wanted to get a drink.
Sure.
I'm good.
Any word on Tetch?
Yeah, he stumbled
into some hospital.
They patched him up,
shipped him back to Arkham.
You know, I'd actually like to
get back to being a detective.
Do some good,
old-fashioned police work.
The kind that doesn't involve
secret cults or blood viruses.
- Do we have anything like that?
- Not really.
Half the force is coming off
24-hour shifts, but we could, uh,
hit the streets like a
couple of beat cops.
See if we could stir
up some trouble?
I don't know. Seems
kinda beneath me.
You know, seeing as I'm the best
cop you've ever worked with and all.
I was just telling you
whatever crap came to mind
so you wouldn't punch
a hole through my head.
Like a hostage negotiation.
You just tell someone
what they want to hear.
Sure, sure.
- Now if you didn't have the virus...
- Is that right?
It was so good.
Money! Now!
- Dad?
- It's okay, sweetheart.
Now!
No!
English-SDH